{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Quakers and Anglicans fought over this state’s governorship in Cary’s Rebellion. This modern-day state was home to the Albemarle Settlements, and its Halifax Resolves were the first official resolution calling for American independence. This state and a southern neighbor were granted to Robert Heath as Cape Fear in 1629. The Battle of Guilford Court House took place in, for ten points, what Mid-Atlantic state with capital at Raleigh?",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "After putting down Quintus Cassius Longinus’s rebellion in Spain, this man received a triumph and was Master of the Horse twice under Julius Caesar. This man, who served as the last pontifex maximus of the Roman Republic after Caesar’s death, was overthrown after trying to claim Sicily after the final defeat of Sextus Pompey, setting the stage for the final showdown between Antony and Octavian. For ten points, name this third member of the Second Triumvirate.",
      "answer": "Marcus Aemilius Lepidus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Mappin & Webb marketed the “Famed Campaign” brand of these objects after the Battle of Omdurman, and Joseph Stalin named a brand of these objects “Pobeda,” or “Victory,” to be sold starting in 1946. The technology behind these objects was revolutionized by the use of crystals that oscillate at a frequency of two to the 15th power hertz, leading to the so-called “Quartz Crisis” for slow-adapting competitors of Seiko and Citizen. New York City’s Canal Street is home to counterfeit vendors of, for ten points, what personal timepieces produced by Rolex?",
      "answer": "watches do not"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a speech at Boston’s Home Market Club, this man noted that the U.S. needs to “put an end to false economics which lure humanity to utter chaos” in a speech that opens by blaming a “fever [that] has rendered men irrational.” This man argued that “America’s present need is not heroics, but healing; not nostrums, but” the slogan of his presidential campaign, in which he beat Leonard Wood on the tenth ballot at the nominating convention and beat James Cox in the election. For ten points, name this US president who promised a “Return to Normalcy” after World War I.",
      "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s reign, the Lingqu Canal was built as part of a system connecting the Yangtze and Pearl Rivers. This man survived an assassination attempt in which a heavy metal cone was dropped on his carriage from atop a mountain. This man, who was advised by chancellor Li Si to make Legalism the official ideology, targeted the Hundred Schools of Thought by burning Confucian books and buried their scholars alive. The Terracotta Army was commissioned by, for ten points, what first emperor of a unified China?",
      "answer": [
        "Qin Shi Huangdi",
        "Ying Zheng",
        "Zhao Zheng",
        "King Zheng of Qin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A photograph taken in this city shows two men wielding pistols taking cover behind a forklift. An event in this city was partially fueled by a store owner receiving probation for the murder of Latasha Harlins over the suspected theft of a $1.79 bottle of orange juice. During an event in this city referred to as Sa-I-Gu, Richard Rhee and 20 of his employees set up an armed camp to defend the California Market. For ten points, name this city where racial tensions between the Korean and Black communities exploded after four police officers were acquitted for the beating of Rodney King.",
      "answer": [
        "Los Angeles",
        "LA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A black-and-white photo of a 1913 rally is juxtaposed with a photo of this event that was digitally altered by the National Archives for an exhibit celebrating the centennial of the 19th Amendment; the alterations included blurring part of the phrase “God hates Trump.” Vanessa Wruble co-led this event, whose attendance dwarfed that of a ceremony held the previous day. For ten points, name this January 21, 2017 rally, the largest single-day protest in American history, against the policies of Donald Trump.",
      "answer": [
        "2017 Women’s March",
        "2017 Women’s March on Washington",
        "descriptive answers that include the words Women’s March"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Adam of Bremen claimed that the people of Uppsala would sacrifice animals to this god during wartime. Through the process of interpretatio romana, Tacitus equated this deity with Mercury. Animals may have been hung by the neck in honor of this god’s impalement and self-hanging from Yggdrasil to receive knowledge of the runes. The day Wednesday is believed to have been derived from the name of, for ten points, what one-eyed chief god of the Norse pantheon, the father of Thor?",
      "answer": [
        "Odin",
        "Wotan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family calmed an angry crowd at the execution of George Burroughs by claiming that he was “no ordained minister.” The work Remarkable Provinces, which contains selections from the controversial Malleus Maleficarum, was written by a member of this family. During a 1692 event, a member of this family warned John Richards against the use of spectral evidence. The Salem Witch Trials involved, for ten points, what powerful Puritan family that included Increase and Cotton?",
      "answer": [
        "Mather family",
        "Cotton Mather",
        "Increase Mather after “Remarkable” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These people were able to place a poster on a monarch’s bedchamber door at Amboise [am-BWAHZ] in the Affair of the Placards. These people, who attempted to settle Fort Caroline, were massacred two days after an attack on one of them, Gaspard de Coligny. Catherine de Medici probably ordered the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre against these people, the subjects of Louis XIV’s Edict of Fontainebleau and Henry IV’s Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this group of French Calvinists.",
      "answer": "Huguenots"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This monarch offered refuge to the exiled Duke of Warwick and arranged an alliance between the Duke and Margaret of Anjou. In the Treaty of Picquigny, this ruler paid 75,000 crowns to end the Hundred Years’ War. The League of the Public Weal was organized by the Duke of Berry to oppose this monarch. The death of this king’s rival, Charles the Bold, allowed him to annex Burgundy. For ten points, name this French king from 1461 to 1483 whose nickname is derived from his webs of schemes.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis XI",
          "Louis the Universal Spider"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Picquigny was agreed to by Louis XI and this English king, the older brother of Richard III.",
        "answer": "Edward IV"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This thinker contrasted the use of windmills in pre-industrial Europe with power plants along the Rhine River in his The Question Concerning Technology. This thinker, who discussed the essence of art in The Origin of the Work of Art, was labeled a Mitl¨aufer [MITT-loy-fer] following World War II. For ten points, name this German philosopher who defined dasein in the book Being and Time and was a prominent member of the Nazi Party.",
        "answer": "Martin Heidegger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Despite his Nazi membership, Heidegger had an affair with this Jewish German-American philosopher. This philosopher wrote historical philosophy books like Eichmann in Jerusalem and The Origins of Totalitarianism.",
        "answer": "Hannah Arendt"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A “Little” version of this event was presided over by W.G. Boshoff and saw one target say “My Lord, I am a professional agitator.” Percy Yutar was the chief prosecutor during this event, in which one side was defended by Bram Fischer. A defendant in this trial claimed that the Sharpeville Massacre justified the use of force by the oppressed in a three-hour-long speech given by a man who declared “I am prepared to die.” For ten points, name this trial in which Nelson Mandela was sentenced to life imprisonment in 1964.",
        "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Many of the defendants in the Rivonia Trial were members of this group, the armed wing of the African National Congress, that formed in the wake of the Sharpeville Massacre.",
        "answer": [
          "Umkhonto we Sizwe",
          "Spear of the Nation"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A player of this instrument collaborated on the album East Meets West with Yehudi Menuhin at the 1966 Bath Music Festival. Vilayat Khan popularized this instrument, which was played by a virtuoso at the charity Concert for Bangla Desh and taught to George Harrison for songs like “Norwegian Wood.” The score for Satyajit Ray’s Apu Trilogy was composed by Ravi Shankar, a master of, for ten points, what Hindustani string instrument?",
        "answer": "sitar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A sitar is featured in the introduction to “Paint it Black” by this British rock band. This band’s performance at the Altamont Free Concert was marred by the killing of Meredith Hunter by a security guard from the Hells Angels.",
        "answer": "The Rolling Stones"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this siege, Edmund Kirby Smith attempted to attack all of his opponent’s supply depots, including Miliken’s Bend and Lake Providence. Residents built dugouts that the enemy called “Prairie Dog Villages” to hide from shelling during this siege, which ended on July 4th after General John Pemberton surrendered. The Confederacy was split in half after, for ten points, what Union victory by Ulysses S. Grant, the capture of a vital city in Mississippi?",
        "answer": "Siege of Vicksburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Confederate general with this surname waited indefinitely for reinforcements without ever engaging Grant’s forces. Another Confederate general with this last name died at Shiloh.",
        "answer": [
          "Johnston",
          "Joseph Johnston",
          "Albert Johnston"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author’s essay “Blind Nightmare” and book Underground each discuss a terrorist attack on a subway system carried out by the Aum Shinrikyo doomsday cult. That attack also influenced a novel by this author that depicts Aomame and Tengo falling into an alternative version of the year 1984. Hong Kong censored Killing Commendatore, the most recent novel by, for ten points, what Japanese novelist of 1Q84 and The Wind Up Bird Chronicle?",
        "answer": "Haruki Murakami"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Murakami collection including “Honey Pie” and “Super-Frog Saves Tokyo” was inspired by one of these events that killed over 4,000 people in Kobe in 1995.",
        "answer": [
          "earthquake",
          "the Kobe earthquake",
          "Great Hanshin Earthquake",
          "after the quake"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Harry von Arnim saw this man as a rival and thus stole sensitive records from an embassy in France. This man, whose policies included a Sickness Insurance Law and Accident Insurance Law, formed the League of the Three Emperors. This man helped provoke France into war with the Ems Dispatch and launched the Kulturkampf against Catholic power. This user of Realpolitik gave the “iron and blood” speech to the Prussian Chamber of Deputies. For ten points, name this first Chancellor of a unified Germany.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck’s Kulturkampf was carried out through the May Laws, which were written by, and alternatively named for, this education minister.",
        "answer": [
          "Adalbert Falk",
          "Falk Laws"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The fifth of the nine points of this proposal called for an executive-appointed Supreme Tribunal to oversee federal impeachment accusations, and its sixth point affirmed the Articles of Confederation as the law. William Paterson put forth this 1787 proposal calling for a unicameral legislature in which each state had one vote and thus equal representation. The Virginia Plan competed with this plan until the Connecticut Compromise was reached. For ten points, name this proposal at the Constitutional Convention that favored small states.",
        "answer": "New Jersey Plan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The New Jersey Plan included this concept, which was included in Article 1, Section 2, Clause 3 of the Constitution until 1868.",
        "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "20th Century US Vice Presidents",
      "prompt": "Name the Vice President who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supposedly “invented” the Internet before serving under Bill Clinton.",
          "answer": "Albert Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after fighting with the Rough Riders in Cuba.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt or Teddy Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after the death of Warren Harding.",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served under Dwight Eisenhower.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned in 1973 for tax evasion, after which he was replaced with Gerald Ford.",
          "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was appointed in 1974 to serve under Ford.",
          "answer": "Nelson Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served FDR for eight years and legendarily said the Vice Presidency was “not worth a bucket of warm spit.”",
          "answer": "John Nance Garner"
        },
        {
          "question": "Devised a German reparations plan in 1925.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dawes",
            "Dawes Plan"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "European Inventors and Engineers",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Physician who suggested a “simple mechanism” for decapitation in the French Revolution; the device shares his name.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph-Ignace Guillotin",
            "guillotine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German who developed the moveable type printing press.",
          "answer": "Johannes Gutenberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Swedish businessman who owned Bofors and patented dynamite.",
          "answer": "Alfred Nobel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Scottish chemist who improved on the Newcomen steam engine and names the SI unit of power.",
          "answer": "James Watt"
        },
        {
          "question": "German who invented a namesake no-spark combustion engine and died at sea mysteriously in 1913.",
          "answer": "Rudolf Diesel"
        },
        {
          "question": "English “traitor” who memorized the designs of the Arkwright spinning frame to build textile mills in New England.",
          "answer": "Samuel Slater"
        },
        {
          "question": "English engineer of the Great Western Railway who tunneled under the Thames in the 1830s.",
          "answer": "Isambard Kingdom Brunel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian aviation family of Andrei, who reverse-engineered the B-29, and Alexei, who designed the first supersonic passenger jet.",
          "answer": "Tupolev family"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Explorers of the New World",
      "prompt": "Name the explorer who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Brought a few dozen slaves back with him on the Nin˜a and Pinta after his 1492 voyage to the New World.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus or Cristobal Colon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established the Vinland colony as the first European in North America around 1000 AD.",
          "answer": "Leif Erikson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly governed Puerto Rico and sought the Fountain of Youth in Florida.",
          "answer": "Juan Ponce de Leon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mapped the Gulf of Saint Lawrence and claimed Canada for France.",
          "answer": "Jacques Cartier"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crossed Panama in 1513 to become the first European to reach the Pacific through the New World.",
          "answer": "Vasco Nu´n˜ez de Balboa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Accidentally reached Brazil, claiming it for Portugal, on his way to India in 1500.",
          "answer": "Pedro Alvares Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Helped Pizarro conquer the Incas and was the first European to cross the Mississippi River.",
          "answer": "Hernando de Soto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Executed a native guide he called “the Turk” after they discovered that Quivira, in modern Kansas, was not a city of gold.",
          "answer": "Francisco V´azquez de Coronado"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader wrote that he would “take my first step on the road to eternity [and] leave life to enter history” before he shot himself with a revolver. The Integralists supported this leader, who created a monopoly on copper known as (20 pts)",
        "Vale. After announcing that a communist plot called the Cohen Plan sought to overthrow his government, this man threw out the Constitution of 1934 and proclaimed an (10 pts)",
        "“Estado Novo” that lasted until 1945. For ten points, name this president and dictator of Brazil."
      ],
      "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1851, gold was discovered in this state’s town of Ophir. The last autocratic governor of this state, Lachlan Macquarie, constructed the inland city of Bathurst after the crossing of the Blue Mountains. Years after surviving the (20 pts)",
        "Mutiny on the Bounty, Vice-Admiral William Bligh was made governor of this state; he faced the (10 pts)",
        "Rum Rebellion here. In 1788, Arthur Phillip landed the First Fleet near Botany Bay in what is now, for ten points, what Australian state south of Queensland, where James Cook charted what is now Sydney?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New South Wales",
        "NSW",
        "do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This king, who had an illegitimate son with Margareta Slots, founded the University of Tartu after acquiring Estonia in the Treaty of Altmark. This ruler ended a war with the Treaty of Kn´ared after pillaging (20 pts)",
        "Scania, and he made use of auxiliaries called Hakkapeliitta from Finland. This man’s advisers included (10 pts)",
        "Axel Oxenstierna. Count Tilly and Albrecht von Wallenstein were defeated by, for ten points, what monarch from the House of Vasa who won the Battle of Breitenfeld for Sweden during the Thirty Years War?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gustavus Adolphus",
        "Gustav II Adolf"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This civilization’s artwork became known to academics after Melgar Serrano carried out an excavation of Monument A. The Cascajal [cas-ca-hall] block may have been evidence of a writing system in this civilization, whose people were the (20 pts)",
        "first to practice ritual bloodletting in Mesoamerica and became known as the “rubber people” because they could extract latex from trees. (10 pts)",
        "La Venta and San Lorenzo were centers of, for ten points, what early Mesoamerican civilization that became known for building large stone heads?"
      ],
      "answer": "Olmecs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Peace activists during this conflict included Betty Williams and Mairead Corrigan, who shared a Nobel Peace Prize for founding the Community of Peace People. Attacks in this conflict included an ambush at Narrow Water Castle near Warrenpoint. “1 (20 pts)",
        "Para” gained notoriety in this conflict for the Ballymurphy Massacre and the Bogside Massacre, the latter of which became known as (10 pts)",
        "“Bloody Sunday.” The 1998 Good Friday Agreement ended, for ten points, what conflict in Northern Ireland?"
      ],
      "answer": "The Troubles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In December 1945, this man was sent on a mission to China to unify the Nationalists and Communists; his negotiations lasted over a year before failing. Joseph Stalin ordered Poland and (20 pts)",
        "Czechoslovakia to refuse aid from an initiative named for this man. In 1953, this US Army officer was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize, in large part for his work on the European (10 pts)",
        "Recovery Program after World War II. For ten points, name this American diplomat who served as Secretary of State and Defense under Harry Truman and orchestrated aid for Western Europe in a namesake plan."
      ],
      "answer": "George Marshall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s patriotic works include Carillon, a recitation for speaker and orchestra in honor of Belgium during World War I. An oratorio by this man was composed for the Birmingham Music Festival and is based on a Cardinal (20 pts)",
        "Newman poem. Jacqueline du Pre made her 1962 concert debut performing this composer’s Cello Concerto in E minor. A march by this composer of The (10 pts)",
        "Dream of Gerontius served as the recessional for the marriage of Prince Charles and Princess Diana. For ten points, name this English composer of the Pomp and Circumstance marches."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Edward William Elgar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Seth Luther helped lead Dorr’s Rebellion and this city’s unrelated 1835 general strike. Gangs like the Moyamensing Killers and the Blood Tubs reigned in this city, which faced the nativist Bible Riots of 1844 in the (20 pts)",
        "Kensington and Southwark districts. The Reading [redding] Railroad was centered in this city, which was the site of a devastating (10 pts)",
        "1793 yellow fever outbreak. An early government in this city fled to Lancaster after the British victory at Brandywine. For ten points, name this Pennsylvania city where the Declaration of Independence was written."
      ],
      "answer": "Philadelphia"
    }
  ]
}